<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Over the line</title><link>http://axilleas.me/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://axilleas.me/feeds/book.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0200</lastBuildDate><item><title>Coming soon book review - GitLab repository management</title><link>http://axilleas.me/en/blog/2013/coming-soon-book-review-gitlab-repository-management</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="GitLab Repository Management" src="http://www.packtpub.com/sites/default/files/1794OS.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don't already know it, &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/JonathanMH_com"&gt;Jonathan M. Hethey&lt;/a&gt; has recently published a &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/1fTUYMy"&gt;book&lt;/a&gt; 
about GitLab on packtpub. I am in the process of reviewing it, so wait for a new post very soon :)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll attach the preface so you can get a glimpse of what the book covers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this book, we will take a tour of the version control system GitLab, which is based
on Git. It's open source and has many great features that we will learn chapter wise
as listed here. First, we will take a look at what GitLab can do for us, and later we
will see how we can install it on a server and configure it to match our needs.
The next step is to take a close look at the web interface, and then we will learn
how to handle permissions and teams, document our code, track issues, and show
example workflows.
Lastly, we will learn how to perform maintenance for our installation, including the
creation of backups and upgrading to the most recent version. We will also cover
getting in touch with the community and developers on the respective channels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Btw, there is a limited offer on packtpub untill this Friday 3rd January, so you can grab an e-book copy
for only $5.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">axil</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 31 Dec 2013 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate><guid>tag:axilleas.me,2013-12-31:en/blog/2013/coming-soon-book-review-gitlab-repository-management</guid><category>gitlab</category><category>book</category><category>review</category></item></channel></rss>